<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Pattern or president for princes to rule by, and for subjects to obey by together with the rare example of subjects tender and singular care for life and safety of their soveraign : as also for the continuance of sound and orthodox religion in church, and the well-grounded and tempered government of the common-wealth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56721</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12193579</idno>
  <idno type="VID">55937</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240926434</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7181</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12193579</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 872:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Pattern or president for princes to rule by, and for subjects to obey by together with the rare example of subjects tender and singular care for life and safety of their soveraign : as also for the continuance of sound and orthodox religion in church, and the well-grounded and tempered government of the common-wealth.</title>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>"A brief report ... November 24. 1586. and of the answer made in the name of Lords of Parliament ..." and "The second answer made by her Majesty ..." each have caption titles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55937:1"/>
            <p>A PATTERN OR PRESIDENT FOR PRINCES TO Rule By, AND FOR SUBJECTS TO OBEY BY.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With the rare Example of Subjects tender and singular Care for the Life and Safety of their Soveraign; AS Also for the continuance of sound and Orthodox Religion in the Church, and the well-grounded and tempered Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Miller</hi> at the guilded Acorn in St. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls</hi> Church-Yard Where you may be furnished with most sorts of Bound or Stitched Books, as Acts of Parliament, Proclamations, Speeches, Declarations, Letters, Orders, Commissions, Articles of War or Peace, As also Books of Divinity, Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Sermons on most occasions, and most sorts of Histories, Poetry, Playes, and such like. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="character_sketch">
            <pb facs="tcp:55937:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55937:2"/>
            <head>A LIVELY CHARACTER OF THE most Renovvned Queen ELIZABETH, AS It was drawn by a Noble, and Learned Pen of one that was bred under her from his Youth, to her Death.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Will you please to read the Character of this our <hi>English Deborah.</hi> as it was written, and left upon Record by a Learned Gentleman who was bred under her from his Youth, and continued in her Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vice to her Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THis rare Princess (saith he) even while she was a Subject, left patterns that might instruct all Subjects, rather to undergo the indignation of their Soveraigns with the Birth-right of Duty, than with the mutiny of oversensible and Rebellious Affections (which ever, like diseased pulses, beat faster or slower than they should, to shew all to be affected about them;) whereas this Lady, in the like strains, by an humble and constant Temper, had already with true obedience triumphed over the curious Examinations of ascending Flattery, or descending Tyranny, even in the tender point of <hi>Princes Successions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55937:3"/>
            <p>And to make this manifest to be of choice, not chance, even when her step-mother, <hi>Misfortune,</hi> grew ripe for delivery, then was she nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther born crying, as Children be; nor yet by the sudden change from a Prison to a Palace, came she upon that Stage confusedly, barking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all that had offended her: But like one born to behold true Light, instantly fixed her thoughts upon larger Notions than Revenge, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. And in the Infancy of her Reign, she called for <hi>Benefield</hi> her hard-hearted Gaoler, and bad him enjoy, <hi>not a deserved, but free-given Peace, under his narrow Vine; with this assurance, that whensoever she desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have Prisoners over-severely treated, she would not forget to commit the custody of them to his charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, for the next Object, looking backward upon her Sisters Reign, she found Religion changed: Persecution (like an evil weed) sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly grown up to the highest: The Mercies of God prescribed by abridgment of time, and by adding Torments to the Death of his Creatures: Salvation published in many more Creeds than she had been taught to believe: A double <hi>Supremacy</hi> in one Kingdom; <hi>Rome</hi> being the Emperor of the Clergy, and by bewitching the better half of Man, [the Soul] challenging both our <hi>Clergy and Laity</hi> the Stile belonging to the great God, <hi>Rex Regum &amp; Dominus Dominantium,</hi> King of Kings and Lord of Lords.</p>
            <p>This consideration brought forth in her a <hi>Vow,</hi> like to that of the Godly Kings in the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> namely, That she would neither hope, nor seek for Rest in the Mortal Traffique of this world, till she had repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the precipitate ruines of her Saviours <hi>Militant Church</hi> through all her Dominions, and (as she hoped) in the rest of the World by, her example: upon which Prince like Resolution, this our She-<hi>David</hi> ventured to undertake the <hi>great Goliah</hi> among the <hi>Philistius</hi> abroad; to wit, <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Pope:</hi> Whose multitude, not of men only, but of Hosts, she despised, and scornfully rejected that Holy Fathers wind-blown Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition, taking the (almost solitary) <hi>Truth</hi> for her <hi>Leading-Star.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet did she not tear the Lyons Jaws in sunder at once, but began moderately with her own Changelings: She gave the Bishops a proper motion, but bounded and limited, and to the Nobility time to reform themselves with inward and outward Counsel. She revived her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Laws for establishing of the Church Doctrine and Discipline, but moderates their severity of proceeding; giving to Frailty and Sects time to reform: And in the mean season she supplied the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> with Men and Money, as being chief among the <hi>Protestants</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> She gathered and called home from Exile the scattered Hosts of our <hi>Israel.</hi> She took <hi>New-Haven</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> perhaps with hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming <hi>Calice,</hi> to the end that her Axel trees might once again lye upon both Shores as her right did. She refused Marriages, reformed, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55937:3"/> redeemed Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Vanities, who, first glorying in the <hi>Spanish</hi> Seed, published that she was with Child, and instantly offered up the Royal supposed Issue of hers, together with the absolute Government of all her Natives, to the mixt Tyranny of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Castile.</hi> And hereupon King <hi>Philip</hi> took the liberty to exhaust her Treasure to his own ends; Breaks our League with <hi>France;</hi> and in the breach, shakes the Sacred foundation of the rest: Wins St. <hi>Quintins,</hi> while we lost <hi>Calice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrary to all which thought-bound Councels of her Sister <hi>Maries,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> though as yet not out of danger of her <hi>Romish</hi> Subjects at home; threatned with their mighty Faction, and Party abroad; Pestred besides with wanting of Money, and with many binding Laws of her Sisters making; yet like a Palm-tree, under all these burdens, she, like an Heroical Princess, raised her self. And upon notice of her Agents disgrace in <hi>Spain,</hi> his Servants being cast into the Inquisition; her Merchants surprised in <hi>America,</hi> contrary to the League made by <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and our King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, which gave free Traffick, <hi>In omnibus &amp; singulis Regnis, Dominiis, insulis, &amp;c.</hi> notwithstanding that <hi>Astronomical,</hi> or rather, biassed, Division of the World, by the Popes Lines, which (contrary to the nature of other Lines) only kept Latitude for the Advantage of <hi>Spain;</hi> She (I say) upon these Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, receives the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and protects them from the Persecutiou of the Duke d'<hi>Alva,</hi> and settled these poor <hi>Refugees</hi> in <hi>Norwich, Colchester, Sandwich, Maidston,</hi> and <hi>South hampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea again; when this Faith-distinguishing Duke appealed to her self; she binding her self strictly to the words of her Contract, required these afflicted Strangers to depart. Their number was great, and the time allotted but short, and yet their weather beaten Souls were so sensible of the long continued oppressions in their Civil Liberties, and Consciences, as that in their passage they surprised <hi>Brill, Flushing,</hi> and divers other Towns, and expulsed the <hi>Spaniards</hi> out of them; and by this brave example taught and proclaimed a way of freedom to all well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Princes, and Provinces that were oppressed.</p>
            <p>Here also the Reader may observe, that when King <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France</hi> (who was one in the same League) demanded whether mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual defence against all extended to the cause of Religion? She presently answered, that <hi>She both treated and concluded in the same sence;</hi> And if it were required at her hands, She would perform eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry branch of it to her uttermost. The <hi>French</hi> hereupon made war against the <hi>Protestants:</hi> and <hi>Monsieur,</hi> his Brother, secretly protected them by Duke <hi>Casimire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, about that time, at the request of the <hi>Spanish</hi> King, She guarded his Navy into <hi>Flanders,</hi> where it being lost, and she again
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55937:4"/> being requested by the same King, to lend him her own Ships, for the recovery of the <hi>Maritim</hi> Towns which were fallen from him, this Blessed Lady, both denyed this crafty request of a Conqueror, and withall providently refused to harbour any of his Ships in her Ports. Yet in honour of her ancient League with the House of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> she pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished the like inhibition, to her beloved and safe Neighbours, the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therland.</hi> And instantly, with a strong judgment in ballancing of Forraign Princes, she perswaded the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to make Peace with the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers;</hi> And on the other side she disswaded those distressed <hi>Hollanders</hi> from joyning with the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, it is worthy of reverence in this Queen, that she never was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, nor ashamed to aver the quarrel of Religion for a ground of her Friends or Enemies. She made a publick League for defence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, with the King of <hi>Scots, Denmark,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> She banished all <hi>Jesuits</hi> and <hi>Seminary Priests</hi> by an Act of Parliament: Made it Felony to harbour any of them in <hi>England,</hi> or for the <hi>English</hi> to send any of their Children beyond the Seas, to be trained up in <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the loss of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> she resolutely undertook the Protection of the <hi>Neatherlands;</hi> and to distract the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> she sent <hi>Drake</hi> to the <hi>West Indies</hi> with twenty one Ships, who surprized <hi>Domingo,</hi> and <hi>Cartag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na.</hi> And presently after his return with much spoyl, and in triumph (to prevent all possibility of Invasion from <hi>Spain</hi>) she sent him again to Sea with commission to burn all Ships, Gallies and Boats along the <hi>Spanish</hi> Coasts: In which Voyage he brake through divers <hi>Spanish</hi> Gallies in the Bay of <hi>Cales,</hi> which were appointed to withstand him. He took, burnt, and sunk a hundred Sail, which were richly laden with Ammunition, and Provisions. From thence in his Passage to <hi>Cape St. Vincent</hi> he surprised three Forts: Burnt diverse Ships, Fisher-Boates and their Nets. And then sailing to the <hi>Azores Islands,</hi> he there took a great <hi>Carrick,</hi> coming from the <hi>East-Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next year, (as treading in Sr. <hi>Francis Drake's</hi> steps) Captain <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendish</hi> returned from his Journey about the World with the spoyl of nineteen <hi>Spanish</hi> Ships, and of many small Towns in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This and such like Providence did this Miracle of Princes use in all her Wars, by which wayes her wars maintained her wealth, and that wealth supplied her Wars: So that she came ever in State when she deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aid from the <hi>House of Commons.</hi> Neither did she fetch or force Presidents from her Predecessors in those demands; but made her self a President to all Posterities, that <hi>the love of People to a loving Princess is ever even Ballanced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither did she ever by any curious search, seek to enlarge her <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives Royal,</hi> lest thereby she should touch her Subjects in Parliament (by the like self affections) to make as curious an inquisition among their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55937:4"/> to colour any incroaching upon the <hi>Circles of Monarchy.</hi> She would not call out of the <hi>House of Commons</hi> by Writ, to the <hi>House of Lords</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Session; wherein one Mans sudden advancement commonly proves an object of envy to four hundred his equals: Neither would she imprison or release any unjudicially; sometimes striving to master the multitude by the Nobility, and to ballance the Nobility by the multitude, all marks of a diseased, not of a healthful estate in a <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</hi> All which she providently avoided.</p>
            <p>Thus this Blessed and Blessing Lady with a calm mind, as well in quiet as in stirring times, studied how to keep her Ancient underground build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon their first well-laid Foundations: And if she found that any strayed, she sought rather to reduce them back to their Original Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits than to suffer a step to be made over or besides those well-constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and time authorised Assemblies. And by this Policy she ever came upon the Stage, not as a Petitioner, but as a Commander: Hereby she preserved her State above the affronts of the Nobility or People; and became a Soveraign Judge over any undutiful or encroaching Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions either of Nobles, or Commons. She prudently judged that a steddy hand in the Government of Soveraignty, would ever prove more prosperous than any nimble or witty practice, crafty shuffling or impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious forcing humours could possibly do.</p>
            <p>Again, in the latitude which some Modern Princes allow to their Favorites, as supporters of Government, and middle walls between Power and the Peoples envy, it seems this wise Queen ever kept entrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within her Native Strengths and Scepter. And this experienced Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verness of ours made known to the World, by a constant <hi>Series</hi> in her actions, that she never was, nor ever would be over loaden with any such excess in her Person, or defects in her Government, as might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain her to support by a <hi>Monopolous</hi> use of Favourites, as if she would make any greater than her self to Govern by them. And she was so far off from any luke-warmness in Religion that the unexpected Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> fell fatally upon him (as she judged) by the weakness of his Predecessor, King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and the dissolute miscarriages of his Favorites; who, like <hi>Lapwings,</hi> with the Shells of Authority about their necks, were let loose to run over all the branches of his Kingdom, misleading Governors, Nobility and People from the steady and mutual rest of Laws, Customs, and other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient wisdoms of Government, into the Wilderness of Ignorance and <hi>violence of Will.</hi> Among which defects, all fundamental changes (espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Religion) in Princes, would be found (as she conceived) the true Discipline of <hi>Atheism</hi> among their Subjects; all Sacrifices (Obedience ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) being but dear-bought knowledges of the Serpent, to drive Kings and People once again out of Mediocrity, the reciprocal Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55937:5"/> of mutual humane Duties: Prophetically concluding, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever will sell God to purchase Earth by making the Eternal Unity of many shapes, must in the end make him of none; and be forced with loss, contempt and danger to traffique, not for an Heirs place, but a younger Brother's in that Church at whose wide Gates he had (with shame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) already entred in; and under conditions of a Servant rather than a Son, be constrained for his first step to set up the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Faction, providently supprest by himself before, and therein to shake the <hi>Sorb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nists,</hi> who, in all times were faithful supporters of Crown-Soveraignty against those Slave▪ making Commissioners between▪ the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and his, Chaplain, the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, yet with a greater shew of ingratitude, his next step must be to suppress those humble Souls, who had long supported him whilst he was King of <hi>Navar,</hi> against <hi>Rome.</hi> Lastly, to shew that no Power can rest upon a steep place, he must precipitately be forced to send Ambassadors to <hi>Rome,</hi> (with his Sword in his Scabbard) serveily begging Mercy and grace of such irreconciled Enemies, whose endless ends of Spiritual and Temporal Supremacy (this Queen knew) would never forgive any Heavenly Truth, or Earthly Power that should oppose their Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>In her Houshold Affairs she kept the like equal hand, ballancing the Sloath of her great Stewards, and white staves, with the providence, and reservedness of a Lord Treasurer. She kept up ▪Tables for Servants, Sutors, and for Honour-sake in her own House. Not suffering publick Places to be made particular Farms of private Men, or the Honour of her Houshold to be carried into theirs. And withall, by the same Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Auditors she watched over the nimble Spirits, self-seeking, or large-handedness of her active Secretaries: Examining their intelligence, Money, Packets, Bills of Transportation, Propositions of State, which they offered up by their places, together with Sutes of other Nature, in her Wisdom still severing the deep business from the specious, but nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row selfishness of inferiour Officers.</p>
            <p>Besides, All these were examined by grave Magistrates, who having been formerly of her Majesties Treasure in the Secretaries Places, did now worthily become Governors of her <hi>Finances,</hi> as best able to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the selfishness of place, or Person, and the real necessity of her State and Kingdom. This was a fine art of Government, by well cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen Ministers successively, to wall in her <hi>Exchequer</hi> from vast expence of many things, especially upon Foraign Ambassadors, which (she knew) could neither bring reverence nor thankfulness to their Soveraign.</p>
            <p>The answer which this Majestical Lady gave to the <hi>Polish</hi> Ambassador is never to be forgotten, namely, <hi>That she expected a Treating Ambassador,</hi> But he proved (as she told him) <hi>a defying Herald.</hi> This she said at an instance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55937:5"/> to shew how sensible Princes should be of Indignities; and how ready to put off such sudden affronts without the prompting of Councellors.</p>
            <p>But to go on with her Domestick Affairs. How provident was she, out of the like caution, and to the same ends, that even he that oversaw the rest might have his own greatness overseen, and limited too. Whereupon she forgot not to allay that vast Power and Jurisdiction of her Treasurers Office, with inferiour Officers of her <hi>Finances;</hi> and perchance under an active Favourites eye, kept her own. Besides, she watched and checked him in his Marriage made with <hi>Paulet</hi> his Predecessor, and reserved that Mans accounts, and arrears, as a Rod over his Grandchilds Alliance: Yea, she qualified and brought the <hi>Fines</hi> of his many and great Coppy-holds to easie rates, and would never suffer any proposition to take hold of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Dutchy of Lancaster</hi> to her Exchequer, what narrow reasons so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever were alledged of sparing, and cutting off the multiplicity of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers with their wayes and ignorances or corruptions, all chargeable and clowdy paths, which the dealings with Princes Money doth as naturally bring forth as <hi>Africa</hi> doth monsters. But like a provident Soveraign, knowing that place in <hi>Monarchy</hi> must help as well to train up Servants, as to reward and encourage merit, she constantly (to that end) kept that Chancellor-ship-gain of the Dutchy entire, and would not make the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding part of her Kingdom less, to over-lade her Exchequer with any addition of instrumental gain amongst under-Officers, into whose Barns, for the most part, those Harvests are brought.</p>
            <p>Again, by the same caution in all her doings, she made merit pretious, Honour dainty, and her graces passing rare, keeping them to set an edge upon the Industry of Men, and yet sparingly reserved within the Circuit of her Throne, as inherent and tender Prerogatives, not fit to be left at random in the power of ambitious Favourites, or Low-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Counsellors, whose ends are seldom so large, or safe for the Publick, as the native Princes Counsels are, or ought to be.</p>
            <p>For her <hi>Clergy,</hi> with their <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Jurisdiction, She fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the <hi>Arches,</hi> and <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall to take such care one to bound ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that therein limiting themselves, enlarged their Royalties, as the chief, and equal foundations of both their greatnesses. She gave the Superiour places freely, lest by her Example she should teach them to commit Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony with their inferiours, and so to add Scandal instead of reputation to the word of God, whose▪ allowed Messengers they affect to seem.</p>
            <p>Her Parliaments she used, both to supply her necessarily expended Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, and withall, as Maps of Orders or Disorders through her whole Kingdom. In which reverend body, she studied not to make Parties, or Factions by advancing any present Royalist in the House of Commons, to stir up envy against her self among all the rest, and so publish the Crown to use personal practice of hope or fear, in these General Councils of her
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55937:6"/> Kingdom; but by forbearing art, was never troubled with any artificial Brick walls from them; so as their need and fears concurring with her oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, made their desires and counsels concur too, and out of those e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual and common grounds forced every man to believe that his private Fish-ponds could not be safe whilst the publick State of the Kingdom stood in danger of present or approaching exremities.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Council Table</hi> (as an abridgment of all other Jurisdictions) she held up in due honour: She Propounded not her great businesses of State to them with any prejudicate resolutions, which if once discovered, suppresseth, both the freedom of Spirit and of Judgment: But used to open her self clearly, to hear them with respect, to observe Number and Reason in their voices; and then to extract a <hi>quintessence</hi> out of all their concords or discords within her self, from whence the resolutions and directions came suddenly, and secretly forth for execution.</p>
            <p>To be short, She kept awe stirring over all her Courts, and other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, as her <hi>Antidote</hi> against any further necessity of punishments. In which Arts of Men and Government, her Nature, Education, and long Experience had made her to become excellent above both Sexes.</p>
            <p>Again, for the Regiment of her Grandees at home, She did not suffer her Nobility to be Servants one to another, nor did her Gentry wear their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries as in former Ages they had done. Their number, and wealth was moderate, and their Spirits and Power counterpoised with her Majesty, from being Authors of any new <hi>Barons Wars,</hi> and yet reserved, as brave half-paces between the Throne and the People.</p>
            <p>Her <hi>Yeomandry,</hi> a state under her Nobles, and above her Peasants (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to <hi>England</hi>) she maintained in their abilities, and never gave them cause to suspect that she had any intent with any extraordinary Taxes out of the course of Parliaments, insensibly to impoverish, and make <hi>Boors</hi> of them, or <hi>Slaves</hi> of them; knowing that such a kind of Champian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey would quickly stir up the Nobility it self to become doubtful of their own Fences, and by consequence in danger, not only of holding their Lives, Lands, Goods, and Liberties at their Soveraigns indefinite pleasure, but by suspence of those Nursing and Protecting Parliaments, to have all other Native Birth rights, namely, Pulpits, Laws, Customs, Voyces of Appeal, Audits of Trade, Humble and Reverend mention of Coronation-Oaths, legal publishers and maintainers, true maps of Diseases, and Cures through her Kingdom, with many other Cements of Honour and <hi>use,</hi> between So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns and Subjects, like to be confounded, or at least <hi>Metamorphosed</hi> into <hi>Prerogative Taxes,</hi> wherein, neither have the People Voices, nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable returns made them for their Money.</p>
            <p>But this home-born Princess of ours, making her Prospect over these Wildernesses of Will and Power, providently for her self, and happily for her People, refused the broad branch of <hi>Pythagoras's Y,</hi> and chose that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55937:6"/> narrower, but safer <hi>medium</hi> of State-Assemblies, concluding that those two Honourable Houses▪ were the only judicious, faithful, and industrious Favourites of un-incroaching <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it appears that she did not affect, nor yet would be drawn (like many of her ancient Neighbours the <hi>French</hi> Kings) to have her Subjects to give away their wealth after a new Fashion: to wit, without return of Pardons, ease of Grievances, or comfort of Laws, lest her loving People might thereby think that insensibly they should be brought into Bondage as <hi>Slaves,</hi> or Conquered <hi>Out-Lawes,</hi> to the great dishonour to the Legal and Royal State of <hi>Monarchical Government.</hi> From which Example, we which live after this excellent Lady, may, with great Honour to her Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, resolve, that she would have been as averse from bearing the envy of Printing any new▪ Lines of Taxes, Impositions, Proclamations, or Mandates (without Parliaments) upon her Ancient, Coelestial, or Terrestrial Globes, as her humble Subjects possibly be, or wish her to be.</p>
            <p>And surely the reason of cutting between Laws, Kings Powers, and Peoples Liberties by so eaven a Thread, could be no other but a long and happy descent within the Pedigree of active Princes, together with the moderate education of Kings Children in those times: Or lastly, in a <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tessence</hi> of abilities gathered out of those Blessed, and Blessing mixtures of Nature, Education, and Practice, which never fail to lift up Man above Man, and keep him there, more than Place or Power, shall by any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching advantages be ever able to do.</p>
            <p>In which Map, as in a true <hi>Perspective-glass,</hi> this provident Princess, seeing both her own part and her Peoples so equally, nay, so advantagious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly already divided and disposed, she thought it both wisdom and justice to leave them ballanced, and distinguished as she found them. Knowing, that if she should do otherwise, she should bring trouble upon her State, for want of Reverence at home, and should provoke this heavy censure through all the World (<hi>Spain</hi> only excepted) that she endeavoured the raising of an invisible <hi>Tyrant</hi> above the <hi>Monarch;</hi> and to that end had made this step over the Laws, and Customs, into such a dangerous kind of ignorant and wandring confusion, as would quickly enforce Mankind, either to live like exhausted Creatures, deprived of <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> or like the barren Earth without the privilege of a <hi>Jubilee,</hi> which would have transformed her People into divers shapes of Beasts, wherein they must lose Freedom, Goods, Fortune, Language, and Kind, and all at once.</p>
            <p>And if Princes will be induced to use these racks of wit and Power inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly, and thereby force a Free People into a despairing estate, they must either in the pride of their Government, look in some sort to be forced again, either to Sacrifice these <hi>Empsons</hi> and <hi>Dudleys</hi> (as the most popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Act which Princes can do) or else with the two-edged Sword of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,</hi> irregularly to climb a degree yet higher than the Truth, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55937:7"/> these Catterpillers, in eating, or offering up Religion, Laws, &amp;c. to the Covetous, Cruel, or wanton excesses of encroaching <hi>Tyranny,</hi> as though God had made all the World for one Man.</p>
            <p>Yea more, it pleased this Provident Queen even curiously to foresee what face her Estate was like to carry, if these biassed humours should continue any long Reign over us, to wit, Contempt to be cast upon the Crown, Fear among the People, Hate and envy against the Reverend Magistrates, enticement of Domestick Spirits unto mutiny, or Foreign to invade upon any occasion; the Court it self becoming a Farm, manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by drawing up, not the sweat, but even the brows of the humble Subject: And lastly, the <hi>Council-Table</hi> (that glorious Type of Civil Government) compelled to descend, and become Broker for Money, the Executioner of Extremity, better acquainted with the Merchant, or <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical</hi> scraping Revenues of sick and exhausted Kingdoms, than with Foraign Treaties, equal Ballances of Trade, true grounds of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, mysteries of Importation and Exportation, differing Strengths and Weaknesses of Crowns, alteration▪ of Factions, or Parties with advantage, danger of Alliances made to the benefit of the stronger; the (steady though sometimes intermittent) undertakings of the Conqueror, with all things else that concern <hi>Magnalia Regni,</hi> and so apt instruments, not reverently to shew Princes the Truth, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther self-loving Creatures full of servile flattery, even to the main of that Estate wherein they have, and enjoy their honours.</p>
            <p>Which confusion of place and things being clearly foreseen by her, made this prudent Lady to restrain the slavish liberties of Transcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, within Laws and Parliaments, as two unbattered <hi>Rampires</hi> against all over-wrestings of Powers, or Mutinies of People, and out of these grounds to conclude [Prince▪ like] with her Fore-Fathers, that <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structiones Antiquae nec facile evertuntur, nec solae ruunt.</hi> In this <hi>Axiome</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king manifest to the World, that young and unexperienced Capacities are much too narrow Moulds for any large Branches of well founded <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> to be altered, or new fashioned in; the New and old seldom matching well together, let the Cement of seeming Wisdom of either side appear never so equall.</p>
            <p>Now if we descend to inferiour Functions, we there find her (like a working Soul in a healthful body) still, <hi>all in all, and all in every part.</hi> For with the same restraining Providence, she kept the Crown from ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity to use Imperial and chargeable Mandates upon her People, when she had most need of their Service, contrary to the wisdom of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Neither did she, by mistaking, or misapplying Instances (gathered out of the fatal Conquests of her Ancestors) Parallel her present need, and Levies with theirs; But wisely considered that the King and the People were then equally Possessors of both Realms, and so in all Impositions contributers to themselves at first hand.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55937:7"/>
            <p>And when by her <hi>Itinerant</hi> Judges and Justices of the <hi>Peace</hi> in every County, she was well informed of the abilities of her Subjects, and her Enemies threatnings, she then, by the advice of her Privy Council, sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd her Parliament, demanded aid, and never was denied; in return of which loving and free gifts, she laid out those extraordinary helps in repairing and provisional supplying of her Forts along the Coasts, with offensive and defensive Ammunitions. Also she stored her Office of the Ordnance, as a Royal Magazine to furnish the whole Kingdom in times of extremity. Yea, when there were no Wars, yet she kept them full, as an equal pledge of Strength and Reputation, both abroad and at home.</p>
            <p>Lastly, this Prudent and provident Princess, being confident (under God) in these Native Sea-walls of ours, fit to bear moving Bulwarks in martial-times: As also in Civil Traffiques to carry out and in, all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities with advantage; she double-stored her <hi>Navy Magazeens</hi> with all materials provided before-hand with such works and things as requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red time, and could not be bought suddenly with Money. Besides, she furnished her <hi>Sea Arsinals</hi> with all kind of Staple-Provisions, as Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Pitch, Rosin, Tar, Masts, Deal Boards, Cordage, &amp;c. for the building and maintaining of her Navy, flourishing in multitudes of Ships, both for War, and Trade.</p>
            <p>And (as the life of that vast body) she, for the encrease of Marriners gave Princely countenance to all long Voyages, well knowing that they would necessarily require great Ordnance, new Ammunition, and Ships of Burden. Also, the farther to encourage this long-breathed work, she added out of her Exchequer, an allowance of so much in the Tun to the builders of any Ships upward of so many hundred Tuns. She also che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished Fisher-Boats with Priviledges along her Coasts, as Nurseries of Sea-men. She brought <hi>Green▪ Land.</hi> and <hi>New-found-Land</hi> Fishing in repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to encrease her stock of Marriners, both by their taking and transporting of what they took afar off.</p>
            <p>And for Governors of her Navy, under the Admiral, as well in times of Peace as War, She chose her Principal Officers out of the Gallantest Sea-Commanders of that time, whose experience she knew, taught them how to husband and guide her <hi>Muscovy</hi> Company in General Provisions, not as Partners with her Merchants in building, but restraining the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers Riot, or Expence in Harbour and at Sea; How to furnish, or marshal Ships and Marriners, in all kind of Sea-fights for the best advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>Besides, through the same mens Judgments, she made all directions to pass for the divers Moulds required in Shipping between our Seas and the Ocean, as the drawth of water, high or low disposing of Ports, cleanly rooms for Victuals, convenient Decks for Fight or Trade, safe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55937:8"/> conveyance for Powder, and all other Ammunitions, fit Stowage for Sea-Stores, according to the differences of heat or cold in the <hi>Climates</hi> they were to abide in, or to pass through.</p>
            <p>Again, as well to instruct the Captains in their particular duties, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to keep a hand of Government over the large trust and charge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in all expeditions, the Ship with her Furniture, Tacklings, and Men; the Gunners Room with all Ammunition of that kind; the Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swains provision of Anchors, Cables, Canvas, and Sea-stores: The Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, Stewards, and Cooks-Rooms, touching victuals, were delivered to the Captains by Bill indented: The one part being kept with the Officers of the Navy at home, the other was given into the hands of every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Captain, to examine his accounts by at his return.</p>
            <p>Lastly, this great Governess could tell how to work her highest Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals, without noise, to resign their Patents, when the course of time made them in Power, and gain, seem, or grow too exorbitant: Yet she kept up their Command at Sea, and when they were there, made them a limited, or absolute Commission under the great Seal of <hi>England;</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times associating, and qualifying their place with a council of War of her own choosing, and ever guiding the generalities of their Voyage with instructions proper to the business, and to be published at Sea in a time prefixed.</p>
            <p>The Merchant part of her Kingdom was oppressed with few impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The Companies were free to choose their own Officers, to fashion their Trade, who were also assisted with the Name, and Countenance of her Ambassadors, The Customs and return of their Industry and Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, contenting them in a free Market, without any near cutting of her Peoples Industry to the quick.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Flushingers</hi> and <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> for a time did much afflict her Peoples Traffiques, though with small strength; whereupon she first laboured to suppress them by force; but finding the charge to be vast, and the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy casual, she joyned Treaty with the Sword, and by that means set her Seas once again at liberty from all molestation and danger of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates.</p>
            <p>Her Universities were troubled with few <hi>Mandamuses:</hi> The Colledges were free in all their Elections, and governed by their own Statutes: The gross neglect of using the <hi>Latin Tongue,</hi> she studied to reform, as well for the Honour of the Universities, as for her own Service, in all Treaties with Foraign Ambassadors and Poinces: she studied to multiply her Civilians with little charge, and yet better allowance to their Profession.</p>
            <p>In a Word, She preserved her Religion without wavering: Kept both her Martial and Civil Government intire, above neglect▪ or Practice; by which (with a multitude of like instances) she manifested to the World, that the well governing of Princes own inheritances, is (in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55937:8"/> clear house of Fame) superior unto all the far-noised Conquests of her over-griping Ancestors.</p>
            <p>Yet as this wise and moderate Governess was far from encroaching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other Princes Dominions, so neither wanted she foresight, courage, nor Power, both to suppress all insolencies attempted against her self, and to support her Neighbours, who were unjustly oppressed. For she had no sooner perfected her Virgin▪ Triumph over the Pope-hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed invincible Navy, and by that loss published the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ambition to be but weakness and malice, to all <hi>Christendom;</hi> Secured her own Estate, revived the <hi>Neather-Lands,</hi> confuted the <hi>Pope,</hi> turned the Cautiousness of the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes the right way, and amazed the World, but even then, to pursue the Victory, and to prevent her Enemies Ambition, which still threatned the World with new Fleets; even then did this Active Lady, conclude (with the advice of her Council) and applause of her Kingdom to defend her self, thenceforth by invading her Enemy in his own Ports, and no more to attend the Conquerors pleasure at her own Doors.</p>
            <p>Out of which resolution she first sent out the Earl of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who attempted the surprize of <hi>Porto Rico,</hi> and accomplished it with Honour, and so might have kept it, had not Diseases, and disorders proved more dangerous enemies to him than the great Name, and small Forces of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Again, to prevent danger, not in the Bud, but Root, she took upon her the protection of <hi>Don Antonio</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and sent Sir <hi>John Norris,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> with a Royal Fleet, and eleven thousand men to Land, who were seconded with the conduct, and countenance of the Earl of <hi>Essex.</hi> These took the <hi>Buse</hi> Town of the <hi>Groine,</hi> and when they had overthrown all that came to recover it, and burnt the Country, then marched on to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and in their passage, sacked <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che,</hi> wasted divers Villages and Provinces, advanced to the very Gates of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> entred the Suburbs, and plundred them, and burnt threescore <hi>Spanish</hi> Hulks laden with Provisions.</p>
            <p>And to the same end she did, and still meant successively to maintain a Fleet of her own Ships, and of her fast friends the <hi>Neatherlanders</hi> upon the <hi>Spanish</hi> Coasts, not only to impede the return of Victuals, Ammunition and other materials for War, with which the Empire of <hi>Germany, Poland,</hi> and the <hi>Hanse towns,</hi> did usually (and fatally to themselves as it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proved) furnish this growing <hi>Monarch;</hi> but also to keep his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, which was building and riding in many Havens, from a possibility of making Head in any one place whereby to annoy her: And lastly, to set such a charge upon the wasting home of his <hi>Indian Fleets,</hi> as might (in some measure) moderate and qualifie the fearful abundance, which else, was like enough to spread infection through the soundest Counsels, and Counsellors of all her Neighbouring Princes.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55937:9"/>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>Henry</hi> the third (encouraged by her Example and success) did encounter the <hi>Guisards,</hi> a strong <hi>Faction</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> supported by <hi>Spain.</hi> And when that King was treacherously slain, and the <hi>Leaguers</hi> in Arms under the <hi>Spaniards</hi> protection, then did our Queen providently take opportunity to change the seat of her Wars, and assisted <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, the succeeding King by the Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> untill he was able to subsist by himself, and till, by her support, he was strengthned both to overthrow the <hi>League,</hi> and to become a second Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance against the great and vast desires of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither did she rest here, nor give him a breathing time, but with a Fleet of one Hundred and fifty Sail, and a strong Land Army, she sent the Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> and the Admiral of <hi>England</hi> to invade <hi>Spain</hi> it self: These took <hi>Cales,</hi> spoiled the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Fleet, consisting of twenty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and fifty nine Ships, the Riches whereof were valued at twelve Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Duckets. And immediately after, she sent the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> with a Fleet to the <hi>Azores Islands,</hi> In which voyage he sacked <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> and took Prizes to the value of four hundred thousand Duckets at the least.</p>
            <p>Now when this <hi>Spanish</hi> Invader found himself thus well paid with his own Coin, he was forced to divert the provoked hand of that famous Queen which she held over him, by stirring up the Earl of <hi>Tyr-Owen,</hi> and the <hi>Irish</hi> to rebel against her; for which end he sent money, and some Forces under <hi>Don John de Aquila:</hi> But this Lady, first by <hi>Essex,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Mont-joy,</hi> overthrew the <hi>Irish,</hi> and sent home the <hi>Spaniards</hi> well recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensed with loss and dishonour for assisting her Rebels.</p>
            <p>By these and the like active courses of hers in successive and successful undertakings, this provident Lady both bore out the charge of all those expeditions; requited <hi>Spains</hi> Invasion, clipped the dreadful wings of this growing <hi>Monarch,</hi> and made his Credit swell in all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-Banks in <hi>Europe,</hi> causing withal as low an ebb of his Treasure.</p>
            <p>Again, by her thus imprisoning the Lion in his own Den, She did not only lessen his Reputation (a chief strength of growing <hi>Monarchs</hi>) but discovered such a light, as, perchance might have forced him in time to dispute the Titles of his Usurpations at home, and have given <hi>Portugal, Aragon,</hi> and <hi>Granada</hi> opportunity to plead their Rights with <hi>Castile</hi> in the Court of <hi>Mars,</hi> (as since we see <hi>Portugal</hi> hath done) and freed its neck from bearing the Yoak of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you see how our famous <hi>Judith</hi> hath dispersed and dispelled the terror of this <hi>Holophernes</hi> like a Cloud full of wind, and by a Princely wakefulness preserved all those Soveraign States that were in League with her, from the dangerous temptations of Power, Wealth, and Practice by which the growing <hi>Monarchs</hi> do often entangle the inferiour, yet So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Princes.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55937:9"/>
            <p>Besides, in honour of her be it spoken, did not this Mirror of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> by restraining that natural Ambition of gotting other Princes Rights, within the Natural Bounds of well Governing her own, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Beam of such credit, as most of the Kings or States then Reigning, freely yielded, both to weigh their own interests within the Scales of her Judgment, and besides, to assist her in bounding out the Imperial <hi>Meers</hi> of all Princes by the Antient Precession of Right and power.</p>
            <p>Lastly, did she not purchase the like Reputation, even among the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, and by it destroyed a Nest which this aspiring <hi>Monarch</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> began to build in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> For she, thinking it no Wisdom to look on, and see his <hi>Spanish</hi> Pistols to pierce into so high a Mountain of Forces, and dispose of them at his pleasure, providently opened that strong Monarchs eyes to discover how craftily the weaker wrought his ends, at the cost of all defective and sleepy Princes about her?</p>
            <p>Yet did not this Soveraign Lady intercept his Designs from under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vain refuge; But disappointed him by a gallant Factor of her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, in a League of Traffique, and prevailed to make his Ambassador, landed at <hi>Ragusa,</hi> and housed in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and all under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Ferrat Bassa,</hi> the chief <hi>Visier,</hi> yet, and upon a contract of thirty thousand <hi>Zecchins</hi> already paid him, glad to return, and Ship himself away with more haste than he Landed.</p>
            <p>Besides, which Reputation given to her Name by the <hi>Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or</hi> in this particular, She generally got power to keep this fearful Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the half-Moon, waving in such a manner over all the King of <hi>Spains</hi> designs, as that he durst move no where against his Neighbouring Christian Princes for fear of being encompassed within the Horns of the Heathen <hi>Crescent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore to conclude: These <hi>Heroical</hi> Enterprises abroad, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Reformation of her, States at home: The resining of the <hi>English</hi> Sandard, embased by her Sister <hi>Mary:</hi> The preservation of her Crown-Revenue entire. Her great Wisdom in the change of Laws with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change of dangers: The timely and Princely help she gave to King <hi>H.</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> when he had nothing but the Town of <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p</hi> left him, his credit and Means being utterly exhausted, and so that brave King ready either to take the Sea and escape, or to fly for Succour into <hi>Engl.</hi> Also her constant Establishment of Religion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Her driving the <hi>Spanish</hi> Forces thence, who were Maliciously sent, as well to stir up her Subjects to rebell against her, as to maintain and support them therein; together with the former recited particulars, howsoever improperly dispersed, or bundled up together, yet are in their natures of so rare a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55937:10"/> Wisdom, that (probably) they will be more and more admired, and that justly, in this excellent Princess, even many Ages after her Death.</p>
            <p>Upon occasion she professed that she preferred her Coffin before her Cradle; her Burial day before her Birth day. As <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7. 1.</p>
            <p>The Love of this unparalell'd Queen to her people in general, and her tender care over the poor and oppressed in particular was admirable, and incomparable. Her ears were always open to their complaints, and her Hands stretched forth to receive their Petitions. Her manner was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to commend their causes to her Council, and Judges, to whom she u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to say: <q>
                  <hi>Have a care of my People, You have my place. Do you to them that which I ought to do, They are my People, yet every one oppresseth them, and spoyls them without Mercy. They cannot help themselves, nor revenge their own quarrel. See to them, I pray you, see to them, for they are my charge: Them do I Charge you with, even as God hath committed them to me: I care not for my self, my Life is not dear unto me. My care is for my People. If you knew the care I have for them you might easily discern that I take no great joy in wearing the Crown.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55937:10"/>
               <head>The greatest difficulty that her Majesty met with, during all the time of her happy Reign, was the business about the <hi>Scottish Queen,</hi> concerning which the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Assembled in Parliament, Presented unto her Majesty in her Presence-Chamber at <hi>Richmond, November</hi> the 12<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> 1586. In the 25<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> Year of her Majesties Reign, a Petition; Before the Delivery whereof, the Lord Chancellor spake to this Effect.</head>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">THat the Lords and Commons having of a long time, to their intollerable Grief, found in how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Practices the <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> had compassed the destruction of her Majesties most Royal Person (in whose safety, next under God, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged their chiefest felicity to consist) thereby, not only to bereave them of the true and sincere Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in this Realm professed, and established; But to bring back again this Noble Realm into the Thraldom of <hi>Romish Tyranny,</hi> and to overthrow the happy Estate thereof, wherein, although her highness of her abundant gracious natural Clemency and Princely Magnanimity, hath either lightly passed them over, or with no small Indulgence tollerated, notwithstanding the frequent and earnest instance of her Nobility, and Commons, in sundry Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments heretofore: And farther, hath protected her from the Violent pursuit of her own People: Yet she, as a Person obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in Malice (as it appears) continued her former practises,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55937:11"/> as hath been lately manifested by certain wicked conspiracies Plotted by one <hi>Anthony Babington,</hi> and divers desperate Persons, that had combined and confederated themselves by <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Oath,</hi> in a most horrible Enterprize, by Murther, to take away the Life of her Majesty, wherein the <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> did not only advise, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so direct▪ comfort, and abett them, with Perswasions, Counsel, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of Reward, and earnest Obtestations.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Whereupon, her Majesty at the earnest request of such as tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the safety of her Royal Person, and the quiet of the Realm, did direct a Commission under the Great Seal, to sundry Lords, and others of her Majesties Privy Council, and a great number of Lords of Parliament, of the greatest and most Antient Degree, assisted with some of the Principal Judges of the Realm, to Hear, Examine, and Determine the same, according to a Statute made in that behalf, in the twenty seventh year of her Reign. Who, to the number of thirty six, having attended the Execution of the said Commission, and divers dayes and times, heard the Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations against the said <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> in her own presence and hearing) She being permitted to say what she would in her own excuse) did with one consent find her guilty, both in privity and consent to the said Crimes objected▪ and also in compassing the Queens Majesties Death, which Sentence by her own directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon her hearing the proofs and Process in Parliament, was judged to be most honourable and just, and thereupon they all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech her Majesty, that forasmuch as the said Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was the very ground and only subject whereupon such dangerous P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Complots had been founded against h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Majesties Royal Person, and the Estate of this Realm for these many Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs, to the overthrow of sundry of the Nobility of the Land, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d danger of the Christian Religion and for that they could see no hope of her desisting, nor of her Adherents, but that still her Majesties safety must be hazarded, and stand to the event of the like miraculous discoveries.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Therefore, as most humble and instant suppliants, they did upon their knees at her most gracious feet, beseech and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest in most humble manner, that as well for continuance of Gods Religion, the quiet of this Kingdom, preservation of her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and defence of them and of their Posterities, it would please her Highness to take order that the said Sentence might be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, and such farther Direction given, as was requisite in this so weighty a Cause, according to the purport and intent of the said <hi>Statute;</hi> wherein, if she (pursuing her wonted Clemency)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55937:11"/> should now be remiss, besides the imminent danger to her Royal Person, she might by the neglect of Justice, incurr the heavy dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure of Almighty God, as by sundry examples of his severe Justice in the Sacred Scriptures doth evidently appear.</q> Having spoken to this effect, he delivered into her Majesties own hand the said Petition in writing, which he said, had been with great deliberation assented to, by all the whole Parliament.</p>
               <p>Also at the same time there were delivered to her excellent Majesty by <hi>Serjeant Puckering,</hi> Speaker of the House of Commons, such reasons as shewed what apparent and imminent dangers might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to her Majesties most Royal Person, and to her Realm, by the <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> and her Adherents, if remedies were not spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily provided, whereof this is a short extract.</p>
               <div type="dangers_to_the_queen">
                  <head>First, touching the danger of her Majesties Person.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BOth this <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> and her Favourers do think her to have Right, not only to succeed, but to enjoy your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Crown in present Possession; and therefore as she is a most impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Competitor, so will she not spare any means whatsoever, that may bereave us of your Majesty, the only impediment that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds her from the enjoyment of her ambitious desires.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She is obdurate in her Malice against your Royal Person, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding you have shewed her all Favour and Mercy, as well in preserving her Kingdom, as in saving her life, and salving her honour. And therefore there is no place for more Mercy, since there is no hope that she will desist from her most wicked attempts. The rather for that her Malice appears to be such, that she makes (as it were) her <hi>Testament</hi> of the same, to be executed after her Death, and appointeth her Executors to perform it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. She boldly and openly professed, that it was lawful for her to stir up an Invasion against▪ your Majesty, and therefore as upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion Victory may ensue, and of Victory the Death of the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quished: So did she thereby, not obscurely bewray, that she thought it lawful to destroy your Sacred Person.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. She thinks it not only Lawful, but Honourable and Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to take your Life from you, as being already deprived of your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55937:12"/> Crown by the Excommunication of her Holy Father the <hi>Pope;</hi> and therefore it is like she will (as hitherto she hath done) continually seek it by whatsoever means she can.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That she is greedy of your Majesties Death, and preferreth it before her own Life and Safety. For in her Direction to one of her late Complices, she advised (under covert terms) that whatsoever should become of her, that <hi>Tragical</hi> Execution should be performed upon you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dangers_to_religion">
                  <head>The danger of the overthrow of the true Religion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IT is most perillous to spare her, that continually hath sought the overthrow, and suppression of all true Religion, having been infected with Popery from her very Youth, and being after that a confederate in the <hi>Holy League</hi> (as they called it) when she came to age, and ever since hath been a professed enemy to the Truth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She resteth wholly upon Popish hopes for her delivery, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements, and is thereby so devoted to those of that Profession, that as well for the satisfaction of others, as for feeding of her own humour, She will supplant the Gospel, where, and whensoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver she can, which evil is so much the greater, and the more to be avoided, as tending to the destruction of every Soul, and it will spread it self not only over <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> but also into those parts beyond the Seas, where the Gospel of God is profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and maintained, which Interest cannot but be exceedingly weakned by the defection of this <hi>Noble Island.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dangers_to_the_realm">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55937:12"/>
                  <head>The Peril of the State of the Realm.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. AS the <hi>Lydians</hi> said; <hi>Ʋnum Regem agnoscunt</hi> Lydi, <hi>Duos autem tollerare non possunt.</hi> The <hi>Lydians</hi> own one King, but cannot bear two: So say we <hi>Englishmen,</hi> we own one Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> but cannot endure two.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As She hath already by her Allurements brought to destruction, more Noble-men and their Houses, together with a greater multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Commons of this Realm during her abode here, than she could have been able to do, had she been in possession of her own Crown, and Armed in the Field against us, so will she still be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual cause of the like Mischiefs, to the great loss and peril of this State. And therefore this Realm neither can nor may endure her.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. She is the only hope and refuge of all discontented Persons: She is the Foundation whereon all evil-disposed Persons do build their hopes: She is the Root from which all Rebellions and Treacheries do spring, And therefore whilst this their hope lasteth; this Foundation stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and this Root liveth, they will retain Heart, and set on foot whatsoever devices and Plots they have against this Realm, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise would fall away, die, and come to nothing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Mercy now in this case shewed to her would in the end prove Cruelty towards us all: <hi>Est enim quaedam crudelis Misericordia:</hi> There is a certain cruel Mercy: and therefore to spare her is to spill us.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Besides this, it will exceedingly grieve, and in a manner deadly wound the hearts of all the good Subjects of your Land, if they shall see so horrible a Conspiracy not condignly punished.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Thousands of your Majesties most liege and loving Subjects of all sorts and degrees, that have, in a tender zeal of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties safety, most willingly both by open subscription and a solemn <hi>Vow,</hi> entred into a firm, and Loyal Association, and thereby have protested to pursue unto the Death, by all forcible and possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble means, such as this Queen is by just Sentence now found to be: These can neither discharge their Love, nor well save
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55937:13"/> their Oath, if your Majesty shall keep her alive. Of which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your Majesties Subjects are most desirous to be relieved, as the same may be, if Justice be done upon her.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Lastly, Your Majesties most loving and dutiful Commons doubt not but that your Majesty is daily, and duly exercised in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Book of God: So it will please you to call to your Princely Remembrance, how dreadful the examples of Gods vengeance have been that are therein to be found, against King <hi>Saul</hi> for sparing of King <hi>Agag;</hi> and against <hi>Ahab</hi> for sparing the life of <hi>Ben-hadad,</hi> both which were by Gods just Judgments deprived of their Kingdoms for sparing those wicked Princes, whom God had delivered into their hands, on purpose to be slain by them, and therein to be Ministers of his Eternal and Divine Justice. Ye may read also therein, how prudently <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wisest of all Kings proceeded to punish, by taking away the life of his elder Brother <hi>Adonijah,</hi> for the only intention of a Marriage, which gave suspition of Treason against him.</p>
                  <p>Herein we your Majesties most loving and obedient Subjects, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly wait and depend upon your Princely Resolution, which we assure our selves shall be to God most acceptable, and to us no other than the State of your Royal Authority may Afford us, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Arguments of your tender care for our safety under your charge, doth promise to our expectation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55937:13"/>
               <head>To these two Speeches, and Petitions of the Lords and Commons Assembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in the <hi>28th.</hi> Year of her happy Reign, the Queen returned an extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Answer to this purpose.</head>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <p>
                              <hi>THe bottomless Graces, and immensurable Benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon me by the Almighty, are and have been such, as I must not only acknowledge them but admire them, accounting them as well</hi> Miracles <hi>as</hi> Benefits, <hi>not so much in respect of his Divine Majesty with whom nothing is more common than to do things rare and singular, as in regard of our weakness, who cannot sufficiently set forth his wonderful works and Graces, which to me have been so many, so diversly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and embroidered one upon another, as in no sort I am able to express them.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And although there liveth not any, that may more justly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themselves infinitely bound unto God than I, whose Life he hath miraculously preserved at sundry times (beyond my merit) from a multitude of Perils and Dangers; Yet is not that the cause, for I count my self the deepliest bound to give him my humblest thanks, or to yield him greatest recognitior; but this which I shall tell you hereafter, which will deserve the name of a Wonder, if rare things, and seldom seen be worthy of account. Even this is it, That as I came to the Crown with the willing and joyfull hearts of my Subjects, so do I now, after twenty eight years Reign perceive in you no diminution of good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55937:14"/> wills, which happily if I should, well might I breath, but could never think that I lived.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And now, albeit I find my Life hath been full dangerously sought after, and my Death contrived by such, as no desert of mine incited, yet am therein so clear from Malice (which hath the property of making men to rejoyce at the falls and faults of their Enemies, and makes them seem to do that for other causes, when malice and rancour is the true ground) as I protest it is, and hath been my sad, and serious thought, that one, not differing in Sex, of like Estate, and my near Kinswoman, should fall into so great a Crime. Yea, I had so little purpose to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue her with any colour of Malice, that, as it is not unknown to some of my Lords here present (for now I will play the Blab) I secretly wrote unto her a Letter, upon the discovery of sundry Treasons, that if she would confess them, and privately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them by her letters, to my self, She should never need to be called to so publick a Confession, neither did I it with a mind to circumvent her: For then I knew as much as she could confess, and so much I wrote unto her. And even yet, now that the matter is too apparent, if I thought she would truly repent (as perhaps she would easily appear in outward shew to do) and that for her, no other would take the matter upon them, or that we were but as two Milk-maids, with Payls upon our Armes, or that there were no more dependancy upon us, but that my Life were only in danger, and not the whole estate of your Religion, and welfare, I protest (wherein you may believe me; for though I may have many other Vices, I hope I have not accusto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my Tongue to be an instrument of</hi> Untruth) <hi>I would most wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly pardon and remit these Offences.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Or if by my Death other Nations and Kingdoms might truly say, that this Realm had attained an ever prosperous and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Estate, I would (I assure you) not desire to live; but gladly give my Life to the end that my Death might procure you a better Prince.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55937:14"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And for your sake it is that I desire to live to keep you from a worse. For as for my self, I assure you, I find no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why I should be fond of Life. I take no such pleasure in it, that I should much wish or desire it; Neither do I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend such terror in Death, that I should greatly fear it. Yet do I not say, that if the stroke were coming, perchance Flesh and Blood would be moved with it, and seek to shun and avoid it.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I have had good experience and trial of this World. I know what it is to be a Subject, and what to be a Soveraign: what to have good Neighbours, and sometimes I meet with evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willers.</hi> In Trust I have found Treason: I have seen great Benefits little regarded, and instead of gratitude, I have met with courses purposely to cross.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>These former Remembrances, present feeling, and future ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of evils, makes me to think,</hi> That an evil is much the better the less while it endureth, and consequently, that they are happiest that go soonest hence; <hi>and they have taught me to bear with a better mind these Treasons, than is common to one of my Sex: Yea, and perhaps with a better heart than is in some men: And this I hope you will not wholly impute to my simplicity, or want of understanding, that I thus conceited, that had their designs taken effect, I should not have found the blow till I had felt it; and though my Peril should have been great, yet my Pain should have been but small and short: Wherein, as I would be loath to die so bloudy a Death, so I doubt not but God would have given me Grace to be prepared for such an event, whensoever it hapneth, which I wholly refer to Gods good pleasure.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And now as touching their Treasons, and Conspiracies, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Contriver of them, I will not so prejudicate my self, and this my Realm, as to say, or think, that I might not, without the last</hi> Statute, <hi>by the ancient Laws of this Land, have proceeded against her, that not being made particularly to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55937:15"/> prejudice her, though perhaps it might then be so suspected, in respect of the disposition of such as depend that way.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Yea, it was so far from being intended to entrap her, that it was rather an admonition to forewarn her of the danger there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But seeing it is made, and hath the force of a Law, I thought good, in that which might concern her, to proceed according there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, rather than by the course of the Common Law, wherein (if you the Judges have not deceived me, or that the Books which you brought me were not false (which God forbid) I might as justly have tryed her by the ancient Laws of the Land.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>But you Lawyers are so nice in sifting and scanning every word and letter, that many times you stand more upon Form than upon Matter, upon Syllables than upon Sense of the Law. For in stri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>ness and exact following of common Form, she must have been Indicted in</hi> Stafford-Shire, <hi>have held up her hand at the Bar, and been tried by a Jury. Sure this would have been a proper course to have dealt with one of her quality? I thought it better therefore, for the avoyding of these and other absurdities, to commit the Cause to the inquisition of a good number of the greatest and most Noble Personages of this Realm, and of the Judges, and others of good Account, of whose Sentence I must approve; and all little enough. For we Princes (I tell you) are set on a Stage in the sight and view of all the World: The eyes of many behold our Actions. A spot is soon spied in our Garments. A Blemish is quickly noted in our doings. It behooveth us therefore to be careful, that all our proceedings be Just, and Honourable.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>But I must tell you one thing more, that in this last</hi> Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>you have brought me into a narrow strait, in that I must give direction for her Death, which cannot but be a most grievous and irksom burden to me. And lest you might be mistaken in the Cause of mine absence from this Parliament (which I have almost forgotten) although there be no cause why I should wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly come among multitudes (for that among many some may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55937:15"/> be evil) yet hath it not been the fear of any danger that hath kept me from thence, but only my great grief, to hear this Cause spoken of, especially, that one of such a State and Kindred, should need so open a declaration, and that this Nation should be so blotted with spots of Disloyalty: Wherein yet the less is my grief, for that I hope the better part is mine, and those of the worse are not much to be accounted of: for that in seeking my destruction, they might have lost their own Souls.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And even now I could tell you that which would make you sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. It is a Secret, and yet I will impart it unto you, although it is known, I have the property to keep Counsel, but often-times too well to mine own peril.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>It is not long since that mine eyes did see it written, that an Oath was taken, within few dayes to kill me, or else to be hanged themselves: And that it should be performed ere one Month were ended. Hereby I see your danger in me, and I neither can or will be so unthankful, or careless of your Consciences, as not to provide for your safety.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I am not unmindful of your Oath made in the late Association (manifesting your good wills and affections to me) taken, and entred into upon good Conscience, and a true knowledge of my dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for the safety of my Person, and Preservation of my Life, Done (I protest to God) before I ever heard or thought of such a matter. Being wholly Ignorant of it, till a great number of Hands, with many Obligations were shewed me at</hi> Hampton Court, <hi>Signed, and Subscibed with the Hands and Seals of the greatest in this Land, which I do acknowledge to be a perfect Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of your true Hearts, and great zeal for my safety, which doth the more vigorously tye and engage me to be the more careful for the good of you all.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>But forasmuch as this Case is rare, weighty, and of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence, I suppose you do not expect any present resolution, the rather for that it is not my manner in matters of far less moment,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55937:16"/> to return an Answer without due consideration, much more in this which is of such importance, I judge it very requisite with earnest Prayer to beg of God's Majesty, so to illuminate mine understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and to inspire me with his Grace, as that I may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and do that which will tend to the establishment of his Church, the preservation of your Estates, and the prosperity of this Common-Wealth committed to my charge, wherein yet (for that I know delays are dangerous) you shall have our Resolution with all convenient speed, delivered by our Message. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever any Prince may merit of his Subjects, for the approved Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of their unfeigned Love and Sincerity, and that, either by Governing them justly, devoid of all partiality, or by suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of any injuries to be done (even to the poorest,) that do I assuredly promise inviolably to perform, for the requital of your o many good deserts.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This Gracious Answer being thus made by the Queens Majesty the Lords and Commons were dismissed: And her Highness, some few dayes after, having deliberated upon their Petition, and being of a merciful disposition by Nature, and of a Princely Magnanimity, after some conflict within her self about a business of such weight and importance both to her self and her Realm, She sent to her Parliament by the Lord Chancellor, and by the mouth of an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and a right worthy Member of the House of Commons, this ensuing Message to both the Houses, wherein she moved, and earnestly charged them to enter into a farther consideration, whether there might not be some other way of Remedy, than that which they had already propounded, it being so far from her natural inclination.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the Lords and Commons in their several Houses had sundry consultations, both apart and by private Committees, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen specially upon this occasion. And after Conference had betwixt the said Committees, and it was unanimously resolved among the House of Commons, and by the Universal Concord in the House of Lords (the question being there propounded to every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,) there could be found out no other sound and sure means (to the best of their understanding) for the continuance of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, for the Peace and quiet of the Realm, for the safety of her Majesties Royal Person, than that which was contained in their late Petition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report_and_speech">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55937:16"/>
               <head>A brief Report of the Second Application, <hi>November 24. 1586.</hi> and of the Answer made in the Name of the Lords of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Message sent by her Majesty by the Lord Chancellor after her first Answer.</head>
               <p>THe Lord Chancellor, being accompanied with above six and twenty Lords of this Parliament, came before her Highness in her Chamber of Presence, to deliver the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution of all the Lords of Parliament, concerning the Message which he had not long before delivered from her Majesty, for a farther consultation, whether any other means could be thought of, how the <hi>Scottish Queens</hi> Life could be spared, and yet her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Person saved from danger, and the State of the Realm preserved <q rend="margQuotes">in quiet, declared, that according to the Command which he had received from her Majesty, he had imparted the same unto the Lords Assembled in the House of Lords, whom he found by their general silence, much amazed at the propounding thereof, considering that the same had been before in deliberation among them, and resolved upon, and as it appeared by their former Petition presented to her Highness, wherein they had expressed the same Resolution.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Notwithstanding which, for her Majesties further satisfaction, they had entred into a new consultation, and for that purpose had selected a great number of the choicest Persons of their House, to confer thereof, either privately among themselves or together with some of the Commons, which also was done accordingly, and that several times. At all which conferences it was concluded by them all, and also after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by both the Houses (<hi>Nemine Contradicente</hi>) that there could be no other assured means for the preservation and safety of her Majesties Life, and the continuance of the true Protestant Religion, and the quiet of this State, then by the full execution of the Sentence according to their former Petition; instantly pressing her Majesty with many
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55937:17"/> Arguments and Reasons tending thereunto, whereof (among others) this was one. That as it were Injustice to deny execution of the Law at the Suit of any one particular Person, though the meanest of her People: So much more, not to yield to the earnest importunitie, and humble Prayers of all her faithful and loving Subjects. After which he concluded with an earnest Petition for her Majesties Resolute, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination and Answer, for a present and speedy direction, by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, and otherwise also; according to the form prescribed by the <hi>Statute.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="abstract_of_a_speech">
               <head>Here follows the Substance of a Second Speech made by the Speaker of the House of Commons at the same time, by the direction of the whole House.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat if her Majesty should be safe without taking away the Life of the</hi> Scottish Queen, <hi>the same were most likely, and probably to grow by one of these means fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That haply she might be reclaimed, and become a repenting</hi> Convert, <hi>acknowledging her Majesties great mercy and favour in pardoning her hainous offences, and by her Loyalty hereafter make good the fruits of such a Conversion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Or else, by a new strict Guard be so kept, as there should be no fear of the like attempts hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Or; that good assurance might be given by Oath, Bonds or Hostages, as cautions for her good and Loyal behaviour for the time to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Or lastly, by Banishment, whereby the Realm might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided of her Person, and thereby the Perils be farther remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that come to her Majesty by her presence among us.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="response_to_speech">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55937:17"/>
                  <head>These Considerations being duly weighed, did yet appear so light in the Judgment of all the House, that they durst not resolve that there was any security in any; no nor in all of them.</head>
                  <p>FOr, touching her Conversion, it was considered, that if either Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Duty could have restrained her from such heinous attempts, there was cause abundantly ministred unto her, on her Majesties behalf, when she, not only protected her against the violence of her own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who pursued her to Death by Justice, but covered her Honour, when the same (by publick Fame) was touched, and by very hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and Capital Crimes, objected, and proved against her, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Commissary Deligates, assigned to examine the same, and then spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her Life, when for her former Conspiracies, and Confederacies, with the <hi>Northern</hi> Rebels, her Highness was with great instance, by both Houses of Parliament, in the fourteenth year of her Majesties Reign, to do like Justice upon her, as now is desired, and as her Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Practises had then most justly deserved.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the Penalty of this Act (which was sufficiently noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto her) should have deterred her from such like wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, She hath nevertheless proceeded in her former wicked Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises, as a Person altogether obdurate in Malice against her Majesty, and wholly irrecoverable: So as there was no probable hope of her Conversion, but rather great doubt and fear of her relapses, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidivation, forasmuch as she stood obstinately in the denial of matters most evidently proved against her, and now most justly Sentenced for them also. So that she is not entred so much as into the first part of Repentance, which is a taking notice of, and confession of her Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and therefore is so much the farther from the true fruits which should accompany the same.</p>
                  <p>As for a surer Guard and more strait imprisonment, it was resolved that there was no security therein, nor yet in the two other means propounded of Bonds and Hostages; forasmuch as the same means that should be practised to take her Majesties Life away (which God forbid) would aptly serve both for the delivery of her Person, and for the release of her Bonds and Hostages, that should be given for Cautions in that behalf: which being unhappily effected, and to our irreparable loss, who should free the Bonds, or detain the Hostages? Or being detained, what proportion would there be in Bonds, or Hostages, to countervail the value of so preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55937:18"/> and inestimable a Jewel, as her Majesty is to this Realm, and to us all.</p>
                  <p>But she will solemnly Vow and take an Oath, that she will not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing to the hurt of her Majesties Person? She hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy sundry times falsified her Word, her Writing, yea, and her Oaths, and holdeth it for an Article of her Religion, <hi>That Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> of which sort She accounts your Majesty to be one, and all the Professors of the Gospel also. And therefore we have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reason to trust her in that, whereof she makes so small Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Banishment,</hi> that were a step (<hi>a malo in pejus</hi>) from one evil to a greater? A thing so much desired, and thirsted after by her <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents,</hi> and by some Princes, her <hi>Allies,</hi> who sought her enlargement, chiefly for this end, to set her up as the head of a Party against her Majesty, in times of Invasion.</p>
                  <p>To these were added some few other Reasons, collected out of her own Letters, and out of <hi>Babingtons</hi> Confession, who was her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and Instrument, and a chief Conspirator. By all which it did appear, how her own Conscience suggested what might justly fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, in case any of her intended Designs came to light, <hi>viz.</hi> that She might haply be shut up in a more strait and close Prison, as in the <hi>Tower of London,</hi> if that no worse thing befell her. And in that she directed <hi>Babington,</hi> in case that he failed in the Action, he should nevertheless proceed in the residue, which was, the <hi>Death of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty.</hi> He also confessed, that upon the assurance of her Majesties Death, or the arrival of Forraign Forces, he intended to proclaim the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> and that he made no doubt of his desired success. And therefore her Majesties Death being so earnestly sought after, for the advancement of this her Competitor, Her Highness could not remain in quiet and security, if the <hi>Scottish Queen</hi> should continue her Life longer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55937:18"/>
               <head>The Second Answer made by her Majesty, delivered by her own mouth, to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Speech uttered in the names of the Lords and Commons of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Full grievous is the way, whose going on, and end, breeds cumber for the Hire of a laborious Journey.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I Have striven more this day than ever I did in my Life, whether I should speak or use silence. If I speak and not complain, I shall dissemble: If I hold my peace, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour which you have taken would be in vain. For me to make my moan, would be strange and rare. For I suppose you will find few, that for their own particular, will cumber you with such a care: Yet such (I protest) hath been my greedy desire, and hungring will, that of your consultation there might have fallen out some other means to work my safety, joyned with your assurance (than that for which you are become such earnest Suiters) as, I protest, I must needs use complaint, though not of you, yet unto you, and of the cause: For that I perceive by your advises, Prayers, and Desires, there falls out this Accident, that only my Injurers bane, must be my Lives security.</p>
               <p>But if there live any of so wicked a nature, as to suppose that I prolong this time only <hi>pro forma,</hi> to the intent that I might make a shew of Clemency, thereby to set my Praises to the Wyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawers, to lengthen them the more, they do me so great a wrong as they can hardly recompence. Or if any Person there be, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55937:19"/> thinks, or Imagines, that the least Vain-glorious thought, hath drawn me farther herein, they do me as open injury as was ever done to any Creature, as he that is the framer of all Thoughts knows to be most true. Or if there be any that think, that the Lords who were made <hi>Commissioners,</hi> durst do no otherwise for fear of displeasing me, or else to be suspected to be of a contrary opinion, as to my safety, such do but heap upon me injurious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits. For either those which were put in trust by me to supply my place, have not performed their Duties towards me, or else they have signified to you all, that my desire was, that every one should do according to his Conscience, and that, in the course of his proceedings, he should enjoy both freedom of voice, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Opinion; and that what they would not openly declare, they might privately have revealed to my self.</p>
               <p>It was of a willing mind, and great desire I had, that some other means might be found out, wherein I should have taken more comfort than in any other thing under the Sun. And since now it is resolved, that my safety cannot be established without the Death of a Princess, I have just cause to complain, that I, who in my Reign have pardoned so many Rebels, winked at so many Treasons, and either have not produced them, or altogether slipt them over with silence, should now be forced to this harsh proceeding against such a Person. I have also during my Reign, seen, and heard many opprobrious Books, and Pamphlets against me, my Realm, and State, accusing me to be a Tyrant (I thank them for their Alms) I believe that therein their meaning was to tell me News: And News indeed it is to me, would it were as strange to hear of their Impieties, What will they not now say, when it shall be reported abroad, that, for the safety of her Life, a Maiden Queen would be content to spill the Blood even of her own Kinswoman? I may therefore well complain, that any one should judge me to be addicted unto Cruelty, whereof yet I am so innocent, and guiltless, as that I should even slander God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self if I should say that he had given me so vile a mind. Yea (I protest) I am so far from it, that for mine own Life I would not touch her. Neither hath my care been bent so much how to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55937:19"/> prolong mine own Life, as how to preserve both, which I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily sorry is made so hard; yea so impossible.</p>
               <p>I am not so void of Judgment, as not to apprehend and see mine own danger: Nor yet so ignorant as not to know that it were in Nature a foolish course, to entertain a sword wherewith to cut mine own Throat: Nor so careless as not to weigh and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that my Life is daily in great danger: But this I do consider that many a man would put his Life in apparent hazard for the safety of a King; I do not say that I will do so; but I pray think that I have thought upon it.</p>
               <p>But seeing so many have both written and spoken against me, I pray you give me leave to speak something in mine own defence, that before you return to your several Countries, I may let you know for what an one you have entertained so many troublous thoughts, wherein, as I think my self infinitely beholding to you all, that are so careful to preserve my Life by all means possible; so I protest unto you, that there is no Prince living, that ever shall be more mindful to requite so great and good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts. And as I perceive that you still keep your old wont in a general seeking of the lengthning of my dayes, so, I am sure that I shall never requite you unless I had as many Lives as you all: But I will for ever acknowledge it, whilst there is any breath left in my body. For although I may not justifie my many faults and sins to God, yet for my care in Governing of you, let me acquaint you with my unfeigned intents.</p>
               <p>When I first took the <hi>Scepter</hi> into my Hand, my Title to it did not make me to forget the Giver, and therefore I began my Government as it became me, by setling such a Religion, as both I was born in, bred in, and, I trust shall dye in. And yet then I was not so simple as not to know what danger and peril so great an alteration might procure me: How many great Princes, of a contrary Opinion would attempt all they could against me: And generally, what enmity I should bring upon my self, all which yet I regarded not, knowing that he for whose sake I did it,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55937:20"/> both could, and would defend me therein: And for this Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons-sake it is, that ever since I have been so dangerously prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and persecuted, as that I rather marvel that I am, than muse that I should not be; if it were not Gods holy hand that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth me beyond all mens expectation.</p>
               <p>After this I entred into the School of Experience, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously considering what is fit for a King to do: And I saw, that he was scarcely well furnished for Kingly Government, if he lacked <hi>Justice, Temperance, Magnanimity, or Judgment.</hi> As for the two latter, I will not boast; my Sex doth not permit it: But for the two first, this I dare say, Among my Subjects, I never knew a difference of Persons where Right was one: nor never, to my knowledge, preferred for favour whom I thought not fit for worth: Nor bent mine Ears to give credit to a Tale that was first told me. Nor was so rash to corrupt my Judgment with my Censure; before I heard the Cause. I will not say but many Reports might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be brought to me, by such as might hear the Case, yet whose Partiality and Interest might happen to marr the matter (for we Princes cannot hear all our selves) but this I dare boldly affirm; My <hi>Verdict</hi> went ever with the <hi>Truth</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my knowledge. As <hi>Alcibiades</hi> well advised his friend; That he should not give an answer in weighty matters, till he had recited over the Letters of the <hi>Greek Alphabet:</hi> So have not I ever used over sudden resolutions, in matters which have concerned me full near. To which I think you will give your attestations.</p>
               <p>And therefore as touching your consultations and advice, I conceive them to be Wise, Honest, and Conscionable. So Provident and Careful for the safety and security of my Life and Person (which I wish may be no longer than may be for your good) that though I can never give or yield you a due recompence, yet shall I endeavour my self to give you cause to think, that your care and good will is not ill bestowed, and shall strive to make my self worthy for such Subjects.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55937:20"/>
               <p>And now lastly for your Petition; I shall pray you for this present to content your selves with an Answer without An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer. Your Judgments I condemn not, neither do I mistake your Reasons: But I pray you to accept my thankfulness, excuse my doubtfulness, and take in good part my Answer answerless: Wherein yet I attribute not so much to mine own Judgment, but that I think many particular Persons may excell, and go before me therein, though by my Degree I go before them. Therefore if I should say, I would not do what you request of me, it might be peradventure more than I thought: And to say I will do it, might perhaps breed peril of that which you labour to preserve, being more than in your own Wisdoms and Discretions would seem convenient, Circumstances of Place and Time being duly consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Courteous Reader.</hi> These Books following are Printed for, and sold by <hi>William Miller</hi> at the guilded Acorn in <hi>St.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>ASsemblies Annotations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Juvenal</hi> with Cuts by Sir <hi>Robert Stapleton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ambrose</hi>'s <hi>works.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cradocks</hi> Harmony.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Churchil</hi> Divi Britannici.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elson</hi> on <hi>Colossians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gunters</hi> works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barkers</hi> Sermon, <hi>Isa.</hi> 9. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. B.</hi> Sermon, Survey of Man, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dod</hi> on the Lords Prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Medice Cura Teipsum,</hi> or the Apothecaries Plea against Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tor <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Meret.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cradocks</hi> Knowledge and Practice, <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arte.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Principles, <hi>Oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:55937:21"/>
               <item>Knowledge and Practice, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Principles, <hi>Oct.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gunters</hi> works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barkers</hi> Sermon, <hi>Isa.</hi> 9. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>J. B.</hi> Sermon, Survey of Man, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dod</hi> on the Lords Prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Medice Cura Teipsum,</hi> or the Apothecaries Plea against Doctor <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Meret.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> Entituled a plain and full Expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Catechism of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Entituled, a Sermon Preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Peers at <hi>Westminster,</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> of <hi>November</hi> being a day of solemn Humiliation for the continuing Pestilence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nat. Hardy</hi> Dr. Entituled, Justice triumphing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Sermon Preached the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi> Entituled, the Pilgrims wish, A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Anne Dudson.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Entituled, a loud Call to great Mourning, a Sermon on the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1661. before the Parliament.</item>
               <item>—Entituled, Lamentation, Mourning and Woe, a Sermon Preached the Lords day after the dismal Fire in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Entituled, the Royal Common-Wealths-Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of Sir <hi>Thomas Adams.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Samuel Drake</hi> Doctor Entituled, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Sermon Preached at the Assizes in <hi>York,</hi> 1669.</item>
               <item>—Entituled <hi>Totum Hominis,</hi> &amp;c. a Sermon Preached the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> at the Assizes in <hi>York.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Marriage of Arts, a Play.</item>
               <item>Miser a Play.</item>
               <item>Bastard a Play.</item>
               <item>Cheats a Play.</item>
               <item>Faithful Shepherdess a Play.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Horatius</hi> a Play.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Polyencles</hi> a Play.</item>
               <item>Combat of Love and Friendship a Play.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fetiplace</hi> Christian Monitor earnestly and compassionately perswading Sinners unto true and timely Repentance.</item>
               <item>English Directory, or Expositor, the twelfth Edition revised and enlarged, by <hi>S. C. Duod.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Compleat Bone-setter, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Templum Musicum,</hi> or the Mystcal Synop, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The famous game of Chess-play, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sheltons Tachygraphia, Latin, Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clarks</hi> Looking-Glass for Persecutors, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>